<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ux | Hakan Tuncer's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.hakantuncer.com/blog/categories/ux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.hakantuncer.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-16T15:05:29+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.hakantuncer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hakan Tuncer]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[hakantuncer@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Implementing an App Walkthrough]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.hakantuncer.com/blog/2016/04/20/implementing-an-app-walkthrough/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T22:23:47+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.hakantuncer.com/blog/2016/04/20/implementing-an-app-walkthrough</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I think most professionals who design product interfaces (both physical or software interfaces) will agree
that simplicity and discoverability of an interface is a big winning factor. Simple and discoverable
interfaces are usually self explanatory and for this very reason they tend to provide great user
experiences.</p>

<p>On the other hand, this doesn&rsquo;t mean we should stop providing documentation or user manuals for our
products. A discoverable user interface with a clean, easily accessible documentation is I think what
every product deserves.</p>

<p>When it comes to user manuals or guides, I&rsquo;m so much in favor of a user manual that&rsquo;s deeply connected or
embedded to the user interface rather than a pile of content parked somewhere completely disconnected from
the actual product.</p>

<p>UI embedded manuals can be designed in many ways, one of which is through a concept called &ldquo;App Walkthrough&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>App Walkthrough</h2>

<p>From a conceptual point of view I knew what an app walkthrough is for a very long time but before I sat down
to write this post I was tempted to call it &ldquo;in-app tutorials&rdquo;. After some searching around the topic, I
discovered that it actually has a <a href="http://www.dtelepathy.com/blog/design/ux-flows-how-when-to-design-app-walkthrough">common name</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>A walkthrough is the process of intentionally revealing functionality to a user.</p></blockquote>

<p>Implementing a successful app walkthrough is <a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/mobile-instructional-overlay/">not an easy endeavour at all</a>.
It&rsquo;s like a double edged sword. If you <a href="http://www.webdesignerdepot.com/2014/07/how-to-design-a-successful-web-app-walkthrough/">get it right</a>
it&rsquo;s all unicorns and butterflies. If you get it wrong you can do more harm than good.</p>

<h2>Implementing one for Hackathon Planner</h2>

<p>A couple of days ago I started flirting with the idea of implementing a walkthough for the <a href="https://github.com/hakant/HackathonPlanner">Hackathon
Planner</a>. This is what came out:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/App_Walkthrough/Hackathon-Planner-Walkthrough.gif" alt="Hackathon Planner Walkthrough" /></p>

<p>You can try it by visiting the <a href="http://hackathonplanner.s3-website.eu-central-1.amazonaws.com/">Hackathon Planner preview website</a>.
It is designed to be viewed only once and then gets out of the way forever. There are two things that I still
want to add to this:</p>

<ul>
<li>A quick opt out button on each individual step of the walkthough so that users have an easy way to exit
the tutorial without being forced to complete it.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><strong>Update:</strong> Right after I wrote this blog post, I came across a tutorial that&rsquo;s built into GitHub Desktop (for
Mac). See the screenshot below. Clicking &ldquo;Got it!&rdquo; takes the user to the next step of the tutorial while
clicking the close button on the top left corner stops the tutorial. It&rsquo;s brilliant.
<br/><br/>
<img src="/assets/App_Walkthrough/GitHub_Desktop_Walkthrough.png" alt="GitHub Desktop Walkthrough" /></p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li>An overlay that makes the UI frozen while the tooltips are running. If a user doesn&rsquo;t follow the
tooltip popovers and starts clicking around, things get messy (and this is bound to happen if I
know anything about users).</li>
</ul>


<h2>Show me the code</h2>

<p>Inside the Aurelia app, I&rsquo;ve created a component called &ldquo;<em>TooltipService</em>&rdquo; which is responsible for
orchestrating the walkthrough. There&rsquo;s also a separate data holder class &ldquo;<em>Tooltips</em>&rdquo; that declaratively defines all walkthrough
steps and their contents, positions etc.</p>

<p>Tooltips are created using the <a href="http://v4-alpha.getbootstrap.com/components/popovers/">popover component from Bootstrap 4</a>
(still in alpha at the time of this writing).</p>

<br/>


<script src="https://gist.github.com/hakant/48a5b7c5a4e4f34102f393fbd80dc783.js"></script>




<br/>


<script src="https://gist.github.com/hakant/36345d12467d304e29e444430a8bf747.js"></script>


<p></p>

<p>~Hakan</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
