<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Microsoft | Hakan Tuncer's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://hakant.github.io//blog/categories/microsoft/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hakant.github.io//"/>
  <updated>2014-01-29T23:36:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://hakant.github.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hakan Tuncer]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[hakantuncer@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microsoft BUILD Conference 2012 – Thoughts &amp; Highlights]]></title>
    <link href="http://hakant.github.io//blog/2014/01/25/microsoft-build-conference-2012-thoughts-and-highlights/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T18:29:03+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hakant.github.io//blog/2014/01/25/microsoft-build-conference-2012-thoughts-and-highlights</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Microsoft is heading towards a new era with it’s Windows ecosystem and Azure cloud platform.</p>

<h2>Azure adoption on fire</h2>


<p>It’s been repeated several times during the conference that Microsoft is surprised by the demand to their Windows Azure cloud computing platform. In his session, Mark Russinovich mentioned that getting a new  Azure datacenter up and running from the decision phase to reality takes about one and a half years and at the moment they’re constantly investing in new datacenters.</p>

<h2>Weak Windows Store App ecosystem</h2>


<p>On the other hand, the new Windows ecosystem, Windows RT and Windows Phone, are pretty latecomers in the market where iOS and Android devices heavily dominate. These new Windows operating systems and devices have been taken very positively by the tech media  in general but with one big question: Will the Windows app ecosystem be able to catch the momentum and compete with it’s competitors? This has been declared as the weakest spot of the new generation of Windows devices and Microsoft is well aware of it.</p>

<h2>Microsoft is Opening Up – A Mindset Shift</h2>


<p>This is the reason why Microsoft is doing everything it can to get developers on board and convince them building applications for the Windows store. They’ve been trying to present a compelling development story from design stage to submitting the app to the Windows Store, trying to make this a joyful experience for developers building Windows Store apps. They’re educating developers, giving them free ebooks, devices and a lot of sample applications. Everything is done for creating a rapid development momentum that will enrich the Windows Store with many applications.</p>

<p>Another part of this story is about  the steps that Microsoft is taking with it’s technical stack. For many years Microsoft had been very exclusionary of software languages and stacks that were not “invented” under it’s control. Every solution Microsoft was offering needed to be 100% Microsoft.</p>

<p>This “not invented here” mentality seems to be fading away. Microsoft has been investing heavily on Javascript. Chakra engine of IE, the TypeScript language and the Javascript API’s of Windows RT are clear examples of this investment. Strange enough, a Windows 8 application can now completely be written using Javascript, CSS and HTML. Smart move to get more developer support, which is now very critical for Microsoft.</p>

<p>Who would think one day someone would be able to run Linux servers on Microsoft datacenters? Or Azure Command Line Tools would be written in Javascript using Node.js. Microsoft is definitely opening up.</p>

<h2>Some Highlights from the Trip</h2>


<p>Monday – October 29</p>

<ul>
<li>It was somewhat stressful to fly on the worst day of Hurricane Sandy. Fortunately the flight was not cancelled. The route was over the Greenland and there was quite some scene through the window.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/assets/MountainsFromPlane.JPG" alt="My helpful screenshot" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
